Valerio La Gatta

✓ valerio.lagatta@gmail.com

in valerio-la-gatta

Google Scholar

I am deeply committed to tackling the complex challenges posed by online harm and disinformation. I combine expertise from computer science and social science and adopt a variety of deep learning, network analysis, NLP/LLMs, and statistical methods. My research goal is to contribute to the development of safer and more trustworthy digital environments.

Research Experience

Northwestern University

Postdoctoral Fellow

PhD Fellow

Evanston, IL

March 2024-Present

- Detecting collaborative influence campaigns on social media
- Drone threat modelling, in collaboration with the Ministry of Defense of Netherlands

University of Naples Federico II

Naples, Italy

November 2020-January 2024

- Detecting false and hateful multimodal content on social network platforms
- Improve automatic fact-checking by detecting previously fact-checked information
- Multi-task learning and eXplainable AI to improve disinformation detection

CourtScribes, Inc. Remote

Research Consultant Jun 2022—December 2023

• Multimodal deception analysis for US court depositions.

USC Information Sciences Institute (ISI)

Research Intern

Los Angeles, CA

Jun 2022-Dec 2022

- Cross-platform harmful content diffusion between YouTube and Twitter.
- Detecting false information on Twitter during Ukraine-Russia war.

AlmavivA Digitaltec Naples, Italy

Research Consultant Jun 2021—Nov 2021

• Data-driven estimation of the causes for unplanned down-times in automotive production lines.

Consorzio Interuniversitario Nazionale per l'Informatica (CINI)

Naples, Italy

Graduate Research Assistant

Mar 2020-Oct 2020

• Spatio-temporal data mining and epidemic diffusion modelling for predicting Covid-19 spread in Italy.

Education

University of Naples Federico II

Naples, Italy

PhD in Computer Science

Nov 2020-Jan 2024

Dissertation: "Knowledge-aware Disinformation Mining"

Advisor: Prof. Vincenzo Moscato

University of Naples Federico II

Naples, Italy

Master's in Computer Science — GPA 30/30 magna cum laude

Sep 2017-Jan 2020

Thesis: "A novel approach to eXplainable AI based on clustering techniques"

Advisor: Prof. Antonio Picariello

University of Naples Federico II

Naples, Italy

Bachelor's in Computer Science — GPA 29.75/30 magna cum laude

Sep 2015—Sep 2017

Thesis: "Privacy and Security in Industry 4.0"

Advisor: Prof. Antonio Pescapè

Publications

CONFERENCES

September 2023 Valerio La Gatta

- C8. Raffaele Russo, Giuliano Di Giuseppe, Alessandro Vanacore, Valerio La Gatta, Antonino Ferraro, Antonio Galli, Marco Postiglione, Vincenzo Moscato. Graph-Based Approach for European Law Classification. In *Proceedings of the 2023 IEEE Internation Conference on Big Data*, 2023 (BigData '23). Paper
- C7. Valerio La Gatta, Luca Luceri, Francesco Fabbri, Emilio Ferrara. The Interconnected Nature of Online Harm and Moderation: Investigating the Cross-Platform Spread of Harmful Content between YouTube and Twitter. In Proceedings of the 34th ACM Conference on Hypertext and Social Media, 2023 (HT '23). Paper
- C6. Valerio La Gatta, Chiyu Wei, Luca Luceri, Francesco Pierri, Emilio Ferrara. Retrieving false claims on Twitter during Russia-Ukraine conflict. In Workshop Proceedings of the ACM Web Conference, 2023 (WWW '23). Paper
- C5. Giuseppe Riccio, Antonio Romano, Andriy Korsun, Michele Cirillo, Marco Postiglione, Valerio La Gatta, Antonio Ferraro, Antonio Galli, Vincenzo Moscato. Heathcare Data Summarization via Medical Entity Recognition and Generative AI. In Proceedings of the 2nd Italian Conference on Big Data and Data Science, 2023 (ITADATA '23).
- C4. Marco Postiglione, Giovanni Esposito, Raffaele Izzo, Valerio La Gatta, Vincenzo Moscato, Raffaele Piccolo. Harnessing multi-modality and expert knowledge for adverse events prediction in clinical notes. In Workshop Proceedings of the 22nd Internation Conference on Image Analysis and Processing, 2023 (ICIAP '23).
- C3. Antonino Ferraro, Antonio Galli, Valerio La Gatta, Vincenzo Moscato, Marco Postiglione, Giancarlo Sperlì, Flora Amato. HEMR: Hypergraph Embeddings for Music Recommedantion. In *Proceedings of the 31st Symposium on Advanced Database Systems*, 2023 (SEBD '23). Paper
- C2. Antonino Ferraro, Antonio Galli, Valerio La Gatta, Vincenzo Moscato, Marco Postiglione, Giancarlo Sperlì, Francesco Moscato. Unsupervised Anomaly Detection in Predictive Maintenance using Sound Data. In Proceedings of the 31st Symposium on Advanced Database Systems, 2023 (SEBD '23). Paper
- C1. Antonino Ferraro, Antonio Galli, Valerio La Gatta, Marco Postiglione. A Deep Learning pipeline for Network Anomaly Detection based on Autoencoders. In Proceedings of the 2022 IEEE Internation Conference on Metrology for Extended Reality, Artificial Intelligence and Neural Engineering, 2022 (MetroXRAINE '22). Paper

JOURNALS

- J11. Antonio Galli, Valerio La Gatta, Vincenzo Moscato, Marco Postiglione, Giancarlo Sperlì. Explainability in Al-based behavioral malware detection systems. Computers & Security, 2024. Paper
- J10. Biagio Grasso, Valerio La Gatta, Vincenzo Moscato, Giancarlo Sperlì. KERMIT: Knowledge-EmpoweRed Model In harmful meme deTection. Information Fusion, 2024. Paper
- J9. Valerio La Gatta, Vincenzo Moscato, Marco Postiglione, Giancarlo Sperlì. An eXplainable Artificial Intelligence Methodology on Big Data Architecture. Cognitive Computation, 2024. Paper
- J8. Tanmoy Chakraborty, Valerio La Gatta, Vincenzo Moscato, Giancarlo Sperlì. Information retrieval algorithms and neural ranking models to detect previously fact-checked information. *Neurocomputing*, 2023. Paper
- J7. Antonino Ferraro, Antonio Galli, Valerio La Gatta, Marco Postiglione. Benchmarking Open Source and Paid Services for Speech to Text: An Analysis of Quality and Input Variety. Frontiers in Big Data, 2023. Paper
- J6. Valerio La Gatta, Vincenzo Moscato, Marco Postiglione, Giancarlo Sperlì. COVID-19 Sentiment Analysis Based on Tweets. IEEE Intelligent Systems, 2023. Paper
- J5. Valerio La Gatta, Vincenzo Moscato, Mirko Pennone, Marco Postiglione, Giancarlo Sperlì. Music Recommendation via Hypergraph Embedding. IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks and Learning Systems, 2022. Paper
- J4. Alessandro Barducci, Simone Iannaccone, Valerio La Gatta, Vincenzo Moscato, Marco Postiglione, Giancarlo Sperlì, Sergio Zavota. An end-to-end framework for information extraction from Italian resumes. Expert Systems with Applications, 2022. Paper
- J3. Valerio La Gatta, Vincenzo Moscato, Marco Postiglione, Giancarlo Sperlì. CASTLE: Cluster-aided space transformation for local explanations. Expert Systems with Applications, 2021. Paper
- J2. Valerio La Gatta, Vincenzo Moscato, Marco Postiglione, Giancarlo Sperlì. PASTLE: Pivot-aided space transformation for local explanations. *Pattern Recognition Letters*, 2021. <u>Paper</u>
- J1. Valerio La Gatta, Vincenzo Moscato, Marco Postiglione, Giancarlo Sperlì. An Epidemiological Neural Network
 September 2023

 Valerio La Gatta

Exploiting Dynamic Graph Structured Data Applied to the COVID-19 Outbreak. *IEEE Transactions on Big Data*, 2020. Paper

Teaching & Invited Talks

University of Naples Federico II	
Teaching Assistant, Big Data Engineering	2023
Tutor Computer Programming & Architectures	2023
Teaching Assistant, Big Data Engineering	2022
Teaching Assistant, Information Systems	2022
Teaching Assistant, Machine Learning and Big Data for Health	2022
Tutor Elements of Calculus, Computer Programming & Architectures	2022
Teaching Assistant, Big Data Engineering	2021
Tutor Elements of Calculus, Computer Programming & Architectures	2021
Tutor Elements of Calculus, Computer Programming & Architectures	2020
Tutor Elements of Calculus, Computer Programming & Architectures	2019
Harvard University	
Talk at STAT-E100: "Psychology-driven disinformation detection"	Dec 2022
Netgroup S.p.A.	
Instructor, Social Data Analytics	Mar 2022—Apr 2022
Awards	
Nomination for the Ted Nelson Award at the ACM Hypetext Conference	2023
ACM Hypertext Travel Grant	2023
Recipient of the "Eccellenze Federico II" award for the outstanding academic career	2019
Montoring	

<u>Mentoring</u>

I have supervised approximatively 20 MS students in Computer Engineering at University of Naples Federico II as well as one MS student in Computer Science at University of Sourthern California.

Peer Review

The Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP): 2023

The AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI): 2022, 2023, 2024

IEEE Transactions on Neural Networks and Learning Systems (IEEE TNNLS): 2023, 2024

Expert Systems with Applications: 2022, 2023, 2024

IET Software: 2023 Heliyon: 2023

References

Prof. Vincenzo Moscato, University of Naples Federico II, Italy — vincenzo.moscato@unina.it Prof. Emilio Ferrara, University of Southern California, Los Angeles, USA — emiliofe@usc.edu

September 2023 Valerio La Gatta